<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2014, 2015  Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
 - purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
 - copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.
 -
 - THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND ISC DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH
 - REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY
 - AND FITNESS.  IN NO EVENT SHALL ISC BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT,
 - INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM
 - LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE
 - OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR
 - PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
-->

<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <xi:include href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This document summarizes changes since the last production release
      of BIND on the corresponding major release branch.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_download">
    <title>Download</title>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/downloads/"
	>http://www.isc.org/downloads/</ulink>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_security">
    <title>Security Fixes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  On servers configured to perform DNSSEC validation, an
	  assertion failure could be triggered on answers from
	  a specially configured server.
	</para>
        <para>
	  This flaw was discovered by Breno Silveira Soares, and is
	  disclosed in CVE-2015-4620. [RT #39795]
        </para>
      </listitem> 
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  On servers configured to perform DNSSEC validation using
	  managed trust anchors (i.e., keys configured explicitly
	  via <command>managed-keys</command>, or implicitly 
	  via <command>dnssec-validation auto;</command> or
	  <command>dnssec-lookaside auto;</command>), revoking
	  a trust anchor and sending a new untrusted replacement
	  could cause <command>named</command> to crash with an
	  assertion failure. This could occur in the event of a
	  botched key rollover, or potentially as a result of a
	  deliberate attack if the attacker was in position to
	  monitor the victim's DNS traffic.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This flaw was discovered by Jan-Piet Mens, and is
	  disclosed in CVE-2015-1349. [RT #38344]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A flaw in delegation handling could be exploited to put
	  <command>named</command> into an infinite loop, in which
	  each lookup of a name server triggered additional lookups
	  of more name servers.  This has been addressed by placing
	  limits on the number of levels of recursion
	  <command>named</command> will allow (default 7), and
	  on the number of queries that it will send before
	  terminating a recursive query (default 50).
	</para>
	<para>
	  The recursion depth limit is configured via the
	  <option>max-recursion-depth</option> option, and the query limit
	  via the <option>max-recursion-queries</option> option.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The flaw was discovered by Florian Maury of ANSSI, and is
	  disclosed in CVE-2014-8500. [RT #37580]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Two separate problems were identified in BIND's GeoIP code that
	  could lead to an assertion failure. One was triggered by use of
	  both IPv4 and IPv6 address families, the other by referencing
	  a GeoIP database in <filename>named.conf</filename> which was
	  not installed. Both are covered by CVE-2014-8680. [RT #37672]
	  [RT #37679]
	</para>
	<para>
	  A less serious security flaw was also found in GeoIP: changes
	  to the <command>geoip-directory</command> option in
	  <filename>named.conf</filename> were ignored when running
	  <command>rndc reconfig</command>. In theory, this could allow
	  <command>named</command> to allow access to unintended clients.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_features">
    <title>New Features</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  New quotas have been added to limit the queries that are
	  sent by recursive resolvers to authoritative servers
	  experiencing denial-of-service attacks. When configured,
	  these options can both reduce the harm done to authoritative
	  servers and also avoid the resource exhaustion that can be
	  experienced by recursives when they are being used as a
	  vehicle for such an attack.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <option>fetches-per-server</option> limits the number of
	      simultaneous queries that can be sent to any single
	      authoritative server.  The configured value is a starting
	      point; it is automatically adjusted downward if the server is
	      partially or completely non-responsive. The algorithm used to
	      adjust the quota can be configured via the
	      <option>fetch-quota-params</option> option.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <option>fetches-per-zone</option> limits the number of
	      simultaneous queries that can be sent for names within a
	      single domain.  (Note: Unlike "fetches-per-server", this
	      value is not self-tuning.)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	  Statistics counters have also been added to track the number
	  of queries affected by these quotas.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  New statistics counters have been added to track traffic
	  sizes, as specified in RSSAC002.  Query and response
	  message sizes are broken up into ranges of histogram buckets:
	  TCP and UDP queries of size 0-15, 16-31, ..., 272-288, and 288+,
	  and TCP and UDP responses of size 0-15, 16-31, ..., 4080-4095,
	  and 4096+.  These values can be accessed via the XML and JSON
	  statistics channels at, for example,
	  <ulink url="http://localhost:8888/xml/v3/traffic"
		  >http://localhost:8888/xml/v3/traffic</ulink>
	  or
	  <ulink url="http://localhost:8888/json/v1/traffic"
	          >http://localhost:8888/json/v1/traffic</ulink>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The serial number of a dynamically updatable zone can
	  now be set using
	  <command>rndc signing -serial <replaceable>number</replaceable> <replaceable>zonename</replaceable></command>.
	  This is particularly useful with <option>inline-signing</option>
	  zones that have been reset.  Setting the serial number to a value
	  larger than that on the slaves will trigger an AXFR-style
	  transfer.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When answering recursive queries, SERVFAIL responses can now be
	  cached by the server for a limited time; subsequent queries for
	  the same query name and type will return another SERVFAIL until
	  the cache times out.  This reduces the frequency of retries
	  when a query is persistently failing, which can be a burden
	  on recursive serviers.  The SERVFAIL cache timeout is controlled
	  by <option>servfail-ttl</option>, which defaults to 10 seconds
	  and has an upper limit of 30.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new <command>rndc nta</command> command can now be used to
	  set a "negative trust anchor" (NTA), disabling DNSSEC validation for
	  a specific domain; this can be used when responses from a domain
	  are known to be failing validation due to administrative error
	  rather than because of a spoofing attack. NTAs are strictly
	  temporary; by default they expire after one hour, but can be
	  configured to last up to one week.  The default NTA lifetime
	  can be changed by setting the <option>nta-lifetime</option> in
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. When added, NTAs are stored in a
	  file (<filename><replaceable>viewname</replaceable>.nta</filename>)
	  in order to persist across restarts of the <command>named</command> server.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The EDNS Client Subnet (ECS) option is now supported for
	  authoritative servers; if a query contains an ECS option then
	  ACLs containing <option>geoip</option> or <option>ecs</option>
	  elements can match against the the address encoded in the option.
	  This can be used to select a view for a query, so that different
	  answers can be provided depending on the client network.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The EDNS EXPIRE option has been implemented on the client
	  side, allowing a slave server to set the expiration timer
	  correctly when transferring zone data from another slave
	  server.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A new <option>masterfile-style</option> zone option controls
	  the formatting of text zone files:  When set to
	  <literal>full</literal>, the zone file will dumped in
	  single-line-per-record format.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +ednsopt</command> can now be used to set
	  arbitrary EDNS options in DNS requests.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +ednsflags</command> can now be used to set
	  yet-to-be-defined EDNS flags in DNS requests.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +[no]ednsnegotiation</command> can now be used enable /
	  disable EDNS version negotiation.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +header-only</command> can now be used to send
	  queries without a question section.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +ttlunits</command> causes <command>dig</command>
	  to print TTL values with time-unit suffixes: w, d, h, m, s for
	  weeks, days, hours, minutes, and seconds.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +zflag</command> can be used to set the last
	  unassigned DNS header flag bit.  This bit in normally zero.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +dscp=<replaceable>value</replaceable></command>
	  can now be used to set the DSCP code point in outgoing query
	  packets.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <option>serial-update-method</option> can now be set to
	  <literal>date</literal>. On update, the serial number will
	  be set to the current date in YYYYMMDDNN format.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dnssec-signzone -N date</command> also sets the serial
	  number to YYYYMMDDNN.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named -L <replaceable>filename</replaceable></command>
	  causes <command>named</command> to send log messages to the specified file by
	  default instead of to the system log.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The rate limiter configured by the
	  <option>serial-query-rate</option> option no longer covers
	  NOTIFY messages; those are now separately controlled by
	  <option>notify-rate</option> and
	  <option>startup-notify-rate</option> (the latter of which
	  controls the rate of NOTIFY messages sent when the server
	  is first started up or reconfigured).
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The default number of tasks and client objects available
	  for serving lightweight resolver queries have been increased,
	  and are now configurable via the new <option>lwres-tasks</option>
	  and <option>lwres-clients</option> options in
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. [RT #35857]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Log output to files can now be buffered by specifying
	  <command>buffered yes;</command> when creating a channel.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>delv +tcp</command> will exclusively use TCP when
	  sending queries.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> will now check to see whether
	  other name server processes are running before starting up.
	  This is implemented in two ways: 1) by refusing to start
	  if the configured network interfaces all return "address
	  in use", and 2) by attempting to acquire a lock on a file
	  specified by the <option>lock-file</option> option or
	  the <command>-X</command> command line option.  The
	  default lock file is
	  <filename>/var/run/named/named.lock</filename>.
	  Specifying <literal>none</literal> will disable the lock
	  file check.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>rndc delzone</command> can now be applied to zones
	  which were configured in <filename>named.conf</filename>;
	  it is no longer restricted to zones which were added by
	  <command>rndc addzone</command>.  (Note, however, that
	  this does not edit <filename>named.conf</filename>; the zone
	  must be removed from the configuration or it will return
	  when <command>named</command> is restarted or reloaded.)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>rndc modzone</command> can be used to reconfigure
	  a zone, using similar syntax to <command>rndc addzone</command>. 
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>rndc showzone</command> displays the current
	  configuration for a specified zone.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added server-side support for pipelined TCP queries.  Clients
	  may continue sending queries via TCP while previous queries are
	  processed in parallel.  Responses are sent when they are
	  ready, not necessarily in the order in which the queries were
	  received.
	</para>
	<para>
	  To revert to the former behavior for a particular
	  client address or range of addresses, specify the address prefix
	  in the "keep-response-order" option.  To revert to the former
	  behavior for all clients, use "keep-response-order { any; };".
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new <command>mdig</command> command is a version of
	  <command>dig</command> that sends multiple pipelined
	  queries and then waits for responses, instead of sending one
	  query and waiting the response before sending the next. [RT #38261]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  To enable better monitoring and troubleshooting of RFC 5011
	  trust anchor management, the new <command>rndc managed-keys</command>
	  can be used to check status of trust anchors or to force keys
	  to be refreshed.  Also, the managed-keys data file now has
	  easier-to-read comments. [RT #38458]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  An <command>--enable-querytrace</command> configure switch is
	  now available to enable very verbose query tracelogging. This
	  option can only be set at compile time. This option has a
	  negative performance impact and should be used only for
	  debugging. [RT #37520]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A new <command>tcp-only</command> option can be specified
	  in <command>server</command> statements to force
	  <command>named</command> to connect to the specified
	  server via TCP. [RT #37800]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>nxdomain-redirect</command> option specifies
	  a DNS namespace to use for NXDOMAIN redirection. When a 
	  recursive lookup returns NXDOMAIN, a second lookup is
	  initiated with the specified name appended to the query
	  name. This allows NXDOMAIN redirection data to be supplied
	  by multiple zones configured on the server or by recursive
	  queries to other servers. (The older method, using
	  a single <command>type redirect</command> zone, has
	  better average performance but is less flexible.) [RT #37989]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_changes">
    <title>Feature Changes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  ACLs containing <command>geoip asnum</command> elements were
	  not correctly matched unless the full organization name was
	  specified in the ACL (as in
	  <command>geoip asnum "AS1234 Example, Inc.";</command>).
	  They can now match against the AS number alone (as in
	  <command>geoip asnum "AS1234";</command>).
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When using native PKCS#11 cryptography (i.e.,
	  <command>configure --enable-native-pkcs11</command>) HSM PINs
	  of up to 256 characters can now be used.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  NXDOMAIN responses to queries of type DS are now cached separately
	  from those for other types. This helps when using "grafted" zones
	  of type forward, for which the parent zone does not contain a
	  delegation, such as local top-level domains.  Previously a query
	  of type DS for such a zone could cause the zone apex to be cached
	  as NXDOMAIN, blocking all subsequent queries.  (Note: This
	  change is only helpful when DNSSEC validation is not enabled.
	  "Grafted" zones without a delegation in the parent are not a
	  recommended configuration.)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Update forwarding performance has been improved by allowing
	  a single TCP connection to be shared between multiple updates.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  By default, <command>nsupdate</command> will now check
	  the correctness of hostnames when adding records of type
	  A, AAAA, MX, SOA, NS, SRV or PTR.  This behavior can be
	  disabled with <command>check-names no</command>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added support for OPENPGPKEY type.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The names of the files used to store managed keys and added
	  zones for each view are no longer based on the SHA256 hash
	  of the view name, except when this is necessary because the
	  view name contains characters that would be incompatible with use
	  as a file name.  For views whose names do not contain forward
	  slashes ('/'), backslashes ('\'), or capital letters - which
	  could potentially cause namespace collision problems on
	  case-insensitive filesystems - files will now be named
	  after the view (for example, <filename>internal.mkeys</filename>
	  or <filename>external.nzf</filename>).  However, to ensure
	  consistent behavior when upgrading, if a file using the old
	  name format is found to exist, it will continue to be used.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  "rndc" can now return text output of arbitrary size to
	  the caller. (Prior to this, certain commands such as
	  "rndc tsig-list" and "rndc zonestatus" could return
	  truncated output.)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Errors reported when running <command>rndc addzone</command>
	  (e.g., when a zone file cannot be loaded) have been clarified
	  to make it easier to diagnose problems.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When encountering an authoritative name server whose name is
	  an alias pointing to another name, the resolver treats
	  this as an error and skips to the next server. Previously
	  this happened silently; now the error will be logged to
	  the newly-created "cname" log category.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  If <command>named</command> is not configured to validate the answer then
	  allow fallback to plain DNS on timeout even when we know
	  the server supports EDNS.  This will allow the server to
	  potentially resolve signed queries when TCP is being
	  blocked.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Large inline-signing changes should be less disruptive.
	  Signature generation is now done incrementally; the number
	  of signatures to be generated in each quantum is controlled
	  by "sig-signing-signatures <replaceable>number</replaceable>;".
	  [RT #37927]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The experimental SIT option (code point 65001) of BIND
	  9.10.0 through BIND 9.10.2 has be replace the COOKIE
	  option (code point 10) and is no longer experimental and
	  is sent by default.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The SIT related named.conf options have been marked as
	  obsolete and are otherwise ignored.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When retrying a query via TCP due to the first answer
	  being truncated, <command>dig</command> will now correctly
	  send the Server COOKIE returned by the server in the prior
	  response. [RT #39047]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A alternative NXDOMAIN redirect method (nxdomain-redirect)
	  which allows the redirect information to be looked up from
	  a namespace on the Internet rather than requiring a zone
	  to be configured on the server is now available.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Retrieving the local port range from net.ipv4.ip_local_port_range
	  on Linux is now supported.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Within the <option>response-policy</option> option, it is now
	  possible to configure RPZ rewrite logging on a per-zone basis
	  using the <option>log</option> clause.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_bugs">
    <title>Bug Fixes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig</command>, <command>host</command> and
	  <command>nslookup</command> aborted when encountering
	  a name which, after appending search list elements,
	  exceeded 255 bytes. Such names are now skipped, but
	  processing of other names will continue. [RT #36892]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The error message generated when
	  <command>named-checkzone</command> or
	  <command>named-checkconf -z</command> encounters a
	  <option>$TTL</option> directive without a value has
	  been clarified. [RT #37138]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Semicolon characters (;) included in TXT records were
	  incorrectly escaped with a backslash when the record was
	  displayed as text. This is actually only necessary when there
	  are no quotation marks. [RT #37159]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When files opened for writing by <command>named</command>,
	  such as zone journal files, were referenced more than once
	  in <filename>named.conf</filename>, it could lead to file
	  corruption as multiple threads wrote to the same file. This
	  is now detected when loading <filename>named.conf</filename>
	  and reported as an error. [RT #37172]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When checking for updates to trust anchors listed in
	  <option>managed-keys</option>, <command>named</command>
	  now revalidates keys based on the current set of
	  active trust anchors, without relying on any cached
	  record of previous validation. [RT #37506]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Large-system tuning
	  (<command>configure --with-tuning=large</command>) caused
	  problems on some platforms by setting a socket receive
	  buffer size that was too large.  This is now detected and
	  corrected at run time. [RT #37187]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When NXDOMAIN redirection is in use, queries for a name
	  that is present in the redirection zone but a type that
	  is not present will now return NOERROR instead of NXDOMAIN.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Due to an inadvertent removal of code in the previous
	  release, when <command>named</command> encountered an
	  authoritative name server which dropped all EDNS queries,
	  it did not always try plain DNS. This has been corrected.
	  [RT #37965]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A regression caused nsupdate to use the default recursive servers
	  rather than the SOA MNAME server when sending the UPDATE.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Adjusted max-recursion-queries to accommodate the smaller
	  initial packet sizes used in BIND 9.10 and higher when
	  contacting authoritative servers for the first time.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Built-in "empty" zones did not correctly inherit the
	  "allow-transfer" ACL from the options or view. [RT #38310]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Two leaks were fixed that could cause <command>named</command>
	  processes to grow to very large sizes. [RT #38454]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Fixed some bugs in RFC 5011 trust anchor management,
	  including a memory leak and a possible loss of state
	  information. [RT #38458]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Asynchronous zone loads were not handled correctly when the
	  zone load was already in progress; this could trigger a crash
	  in zt.c. [RT #37573]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A race during shutdown or reconfiguration could
	  cause an assertion failure in mem.c. [RT #38979]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Some answer formatting options didn't work correctly with
	  <command>dig +short</command>. [RT #39291]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Several bugs have been fixed in the RPZ implementation:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Policy zones that did not specifically require recursion
	      could be treated as if they did; consequently, setting
	      <command>qname-wait-recurse no;</command> was
	      sometimes ineffective.  This has been corrected.
	      In most configurations, behavioral changes due to this
	      fix will not be noticeable. [RT #39229]
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The server could crash if policy zones were updated (e.g.
	      via <command>rndc reload</command> or an incoming zone
	      transfer) while RPZ processing was still ongoing for an
	      active query. [RT #39415]
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      On servers with one or more policy zones configured as
	      slaves, if a policy zone updated during regular operation
	      (rather than at startup) using a full zone reload, such as
	      via AXFR, a bug could allow the RPZ summary data to fall out
	      of sync, potentially leading to an assertion failure in
	      rpz.c when further incremental updates were made to the
	      zone, such as via IXFR. [RT #39567]
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The server could match a shorter prefix than what was
	      available in CLIENT-IP policy triggers, and so, an
	      unexpected action could be taken. This has been
	      corrected. [RT #39481]
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The server could crash if a reload of an RPZ zone was
	      initiated while another reload of the same zone was
	      already in progress. [RT #39649]
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="end_of_life">
    <title>End of Life</title>
    <para>
      The end of life for BIND 9.11 is yet to be determined but
      will not be before BIND 9.13.0 has been released for 6 months.
      <ulink url="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/"
	>https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="relnotes_thanks">
    <title>Thank You</title>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/donate/"
	>http://www.isc.org/donate/</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
