<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY Scaron "&#x160;">
<!ENTITY ccaron "&#x10D;">
<!ENTITY aacute "&#x0E1;">
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      This document summarizes changes since the last production
      release on the BIND 9.11 (Extended Support Version) branch.
      Please see the <filename>CHANGES</filename> file for a further
      list of bug fixes and other changes.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_license"><info><title>License Change</title></info>
    <para>
      With the release of BIND 9.11.0, ISC changed to the open
      source license for BIND from the ISC license to the Mozilla
      Public License (MPL 2.0).
    </para>
    <para>
      The MPL-2.0 license requires that if you make changes to
      licensed software (e.g. BIND) and distribute them outside
      your organization, that you publish those changes under that
      same license. It does not require that you publish or disclose
      anything other than the changes you made to our software.
    </para>
    <para>
      This requirement will not affect anyone who is using BIND, with
      or without modifications, without redistributing it, nor anyone
      redistributing it without changes. Therefore, this change will be
      without consequence for most individuals and organizations who are
      using BIND.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those unsure whether or not the license change affects their
      use of BIND, or who wish to discuss how to comply with the
      license may contact ISC at <link
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/">
      https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="win_support"><info><title>Legacy Windows No Longer Supported</title></info>
    <para>
      As of BIND 9.11.2, Windows XP and Windows 2003 are no longer supported
      platforms for BIND; "XP" binaries are no longer available for download
      from ISC.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> could crash during recursive processing
	  of DNAME records when <command>deny-answer-aliases</command> was
	  in use. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5740. [GL #387]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When recursion is enabled but the <command>allow-recursion</command>
	  and <command>allow-query-cache</command> ACLs are not specified, they
	  should be limited to local networks, but they were inadvertently set
	  to match the default <command>allow-query</command>, thus allowing
	  remote queries. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2018-5738. [GL #309]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> now supports the "root key sentinel"
	  mechanism. This enables validating resolvers to indicate
	  which trust anchors are configured for the root, so that
	  information about root key rollover status can be gathered.
	  To disable this feature, add
	  <command>root-key-sentinel no;</command> to
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added the ability not to return a DNS COOKIE option when one
	  is present in the request.  To prevent a cookie being returned,
	  add <command>answer-cookie no;</command> to
	  <filename>named.conf</filename>. [GL #173]
	</para>
	<para>
	  <command>answer-cookie no</command> is only intended as a
	  temporary measure, for use when <command>named</command>
	  shares an IP address with other servers that do not yet
	  support DNS COOKIE.  A mismatch between servers on the
	  same address is not expected to cause operational problems,
	  but the option to disable COOKIE responses so that all
	  servers have the same behavior is provided out of an
	  abundance of caution. DNS COOKIE is an important security
	  mechanism, and should not be disabled unless absolutely
	  necessary.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Two new update policy rule types have been added
	  <command>krb5-selfsub</command> and <command>ms-selfsub</command>
	  which allow machines with Kerberos principals to update
	  the name space at or below the machine names identified
	  in the respective principals.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_removed"><info><title>Removed Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> will now log a warning if the old
	  BIND now can be compiled against libidn2 library to add
	  IDNA2008 support.  Previously BIND only supported IDNA2003
	  using (now obsolete) idnkit-1 library.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +noidnin</command> can be used to disable IDN
	  processing on the input domain name, when BIND is compiled
	  with IDN support.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Multiple <command>cookie-secret</command> clause are now
	  supported.  The first <command>cookie-secret</command> in
	  <filename>named.conf</filename> is used to generate new
	  server cookies.  Any others are used to accept old server
	  cookies or those generated by other servers using the
	  matching <command>cookie-secret</command>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>rndc nta</command> command could not differentiate
	  between views of the same name but different class; this
	  has been corrected with the addition of a <command>-class</command>
	  option. [GL #105]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When a negative trust anchor was added to multiple views
	  using <command>rndc nta</command>, the text returned via
	  <command>rndc</command> was incorrectly truncated after the
	  first line, making it appear that only one NTA had been
	  added. This has been fixed. [GL #105]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> now rejects excessively large
	  incremental (IXFR) zone transfers in order to prevent
	  possible corruption of journal files which could cause
	  <command>named</command> to abort when loading zones. [GL #339]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>rndc reload</command> could cause <command>named</command>
	  to leak memory if it was invoked before the zone loading actions
	  from a previous <command>rndc reload</command> command were
	  completed. [RT #47076]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.11 (Extended Support Version) will be supported until at
      least December, 2021.
      See <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link> for details of ISC's software support policy.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>

    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
