<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY Scaron "&#x160;">
<!ENTITY scaron "&#x161;">
<!ENTITY ccaron "&#x10D;">
<!ENTITY aacute "&#x0E1;">
<!ENTITY iacute "&#x0ED;">
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2014-2017  Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.12.0 is a new feature release of BIND, still under development.
      This document summarizes new features and functional changes that
      have been introduced on this branch.  With each development
      release leading up to the final BIND 9.12.0 release, this document
      will be updated with additional features added and bugs fixed.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_license"><info><title>License Change</title></info>
    <para>
      With the release of BIND 9.11.0, ISC changed to the open
      source license for BIND from the ISC license to the Mozilla
      Public License (MPL 2.0).
    </para>
    <para>
      The MPL-2.0 license requires that if you make changes to
      licensed software (e.g. BIND) and distribute them outside
      your organization, that you publish those changes under that
      same license. It does not require that you publish or disclose
      anything other than the changes you made to our software.
    </para>
    <para>
      This new requirement will not affect anyone who is using BIND
      without redistributing it, nor anyone redistributing it without
      changes, therefore this change will be without consequence
      for most individuals and organizations who are using BIND.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those unsure whether or not the license change affects their
      use of BIND, or who wish to discuss how to comply with the
      license may contact ISC at <link
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/">
      https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The BIND installer on Windows used an unquoted service path,
	  which can enable privilege escalation. This flaw is disclosed
	  in CVE-2017-3141. [RT #45229]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  With certain RPZ configurations, a response with TTL 0
	  could cause <command>named</command> to go into an infinite
	  query loop. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2017-3140.
	  [RT #45181]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>rndc ""</command> could trigger an assertion failure
	  in <command>named</command>. This flaw is disclosed in
	  (CVE-2017-3138). [RT #44924]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Some chaining (i.e., type CNAME or DNAME) responses to upstream
	  queries could trigger assertion failures. This flaw is disclosed
	  in CVE-2017-3137. [RT #44734]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dns64</command> with <command>break-dnssec yes;</command>
	  can result in an assertion failure. This flaw is disclosed in
	  CVE-2017-3136. [RT #44653]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  If a server is configured with a response policy zone (RPZ)
	  that rewrites an answer with local data, and is also configured
	  for DNS64 address mapping, a NULL pointer can be read
	  triggering a server crash.  This flaw is disclosed in
	  CVE-2017-3135. [RT #44434]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A coding error in the <option>nxdomain-redirect</option>
	  feature could lead to an assertion failure if the redirection
	  namespace was served from a local authoritative data source
	  such as a local zone or a DLZ instead of via recursive
	  lookup. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2016-9778. [RT #43837]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> could mishandle authority sections
	  with missing RRSIGs, triggering an assertion failure. This
	  flaw is disclosed in CVE-2016-9444. [RT #43632]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> mishandled some responses where
	  covering RRSIG records were returned without the requested
	  data, resulting in an assertion failure. This flaw is
	  disclosed in CVE-2016-9147. [RT #43548]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named</command> incorrectly tried to cache TKEY
	  records which could trigger an assertion failure when there was
	  a class mismatch. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2016-9131.
	  [RT #43522]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  It was possible to trigger assertions when processing
	  responses containing answers of type DNAME. This flaw is
	  disclosed in CVE-2016-8864. [RT #43465]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added the ability to specify the maximum number of records
	  permitted in a zone (<option>max-records #;</option>).
	  This provides a mechanism to block overly large zone
	  transfers, which is a potential risk with slave zones from
	  other parties, as described in CVE-2016-6170.
	  [RT #42143]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Setting <command>max-journal-size</command> to
	  <literal>default</literal> limits journal sizes to twice the
	  size of the zone contents.  This can be overridden by setting
	  <command>max-journal-size</command> to <literal>unlimited</literal>
	  or to an explicit value up to 2G. Thanks to Tony Finch for
	  the contribution. [RT #38324]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The <command>new-zones-directory</command> option allows
	  <command>named</command> to store configuration parameters
	  for zones added via <command>rndc addzone</command> in a
	  location other than the working directory. Thanks to Petr
	  Men&scaron;&iacute;k of Red Hat for the contribution.
	  [RT #44853]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Many aspects of <command>named</command> have been modified
	  to improve query performance, and in particular, performance
	  for delegation-heavy zones:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The additional cache ("acache") was found not to
	      significantly improve performance and has been removed;
	      the <command>acache-enable</command> and
	      <command>acache-cleaning-interval</command> options are now
	      deprecated.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In place of the acache, <command>named</command> now uses
	      a glue cache to speed up retrieval of glue records when sending
	      delegation responses.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The <command>additional-from-cache</command>
	      and <command>additional-from-auth</command> options have been
	      deprecated.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <command>minimal-responses</command> is now set
	      to <literal>yes</literal> by default.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Several functions have been refactored to improve
	      performance, including name compression, owner name
	      case restoration, hashing, and buffers.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The <command>dnstap-read -x</command> option prints a hex
	  dump of the wire format DNS message encapsulated in each
	  <command>dnstap</command> log entry. [RT #44816]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The <command>host -A</command> option returns most
	  records for a name, but omits types RRSIG, NSEC and NSEC3.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Query logic has been substantially refactored (e.g. query_find
	  function has been split into smaller functions) for improved
	  readability, maintainability and testability. [RT #43929]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dnstap</command> logfiles can now be configured to
	  automatically roll when they reach a specified size. If
	  <command>dnstap-output</command> is configured with mode
	  <literal>file</literal>, then it can take optional
	  <command>size</command> and <command>versions</command>
	  key-value arguments to set the logfile rolling parameters.
	  (These have the same semantics as the corresponding
	  options in a <command>logging</command> channel statement.)
	  [RT #44502]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Logging channels and <command>dnstap-output</command> files can
	  now be configured with a <command>suffix</command> option,
	  set to either <literal>increment</literal> or
	  <literal>timestamp</literal>, indicating whether log files
	  should be given incrementing suffixes when they roll
	  over (e.g., <filename>logfile.0</filename>,
	  <filename>.1</filename>, <filename>.2</filename>, etc)
	  or suffixes indicating the time of the roll. The default
	  is <literal>increment</literal>.  [RT #42838]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>dig +ednsopt</command> now accepts the names
	  for EDNS options in addition to numeric values. For example,
	  an EDNS Client-Subnet option could be sent using
	  <command>dig +ednsopt=ecs:...</command>. Thanks to
	  John Worley of Secure64 for the contribution. [RT #44461]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added support for the EDNS TCP Keepalive option (RFC 7828);
	  this allows negotiation of longer-lived TCP sessions
	  to reduce the overhead of setting up TCP for individual
	  queries. [RT #42126]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Added support for the EDNS Padding option (RFC 7830),
	  which obfuscates packet size analysis when DNS queries
	  are sent over an encrypted channel. [RT #42094]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <option>print-time</option> option in the
	  <option>logging</option> configuration can now take arguments
	  <userinput>local</userinput>, <userinput>iso8601</userinput> or
	  <userinput>iso8601-utc</userinput> to indicate the format in
	  which the date and time should be logged. For backward
	  compatibility, <userinput>yes</userinput> is a synonym for
	  <userinput>local</userinput>.  [RT #42585]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>rndc</command> commands which refer to zone names
	  can now reference a zone of type <command>redirect</command>
	  by using the special zone name "-redirect". (Previously this
	  was not possible because <command>redirect</command> zones
	  always have the name ".", which can be ambiguous.)
	</para>
	<para>
	  In the event you need to manipulate a zone actually
	  called "-redirect", use a trailing dot: "-redirect."
	</para>
	<para>
	  Note: This change does not appply to the
	  <command>rndc addzone</command> or
	  <command>rndc modzone</command> commands.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <command>named-checkconf -l</command> lists the zones found
	  in <filename>named.conf</filename>. [RT #43154]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Query logging now includes the ECS option, if one was
	  present in the query, in the format
	  "[ECS <replaceable>address/source/scope</replaceable>]".
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Threads in <command>named</command> are now set to human-readable
	  names to assist debugging on operating systems that support that.
	  Threads will have names such as "isc-timer", "isc-sockmgr",
	  "isc-worker0001", and so on. This will affect the reporting of
	  subsidiary thread names in <command>ps</command> and
	  <command>top</command>, but not the main thread. [RT #43234]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The Response Policy Zone (RPZ) implementation has been
	  substantially refactored: updates to the RPZ summary
	  database are no longer directly performed by the zone
	  database but by a separate function that is called when
	  a policy zone is updated.  This improves both performance
	  and reliability when policy zones receive frequent updates.
	  Summary database updates can be rate-limited by using the
	  <command>min-update-interval</command> option in a
	  <command>response-policy</command> statement. [RT #43449]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  <command>dnstap</command> now stores both the local and remote
	  addresses for all messages, instead of only the remote address.
	  The default output format for <command>dnstap-read</command> has
	  been updated to include these addresses, with the initiating
	  address first and the responding address second, separated by
	  "-%gt;" or "%lt;-" to indicate in which direction the message
	  was sent. [RT #43595]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Expanded and improved the YAML output from
	  <command>dnstap-read -y</command>: it now includes packet
	  size and a detailed breakdown of message contents.
	  [RT #43622] [RT #43642]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  If an ACL is specified with an address prefix in which the
	  prefix length is longer than the address portion (for example,
	  192.0.2.1/8), it will now be treated as a fatal error during
	  configuration. [RT #43367]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Due to some incorrectly deleted code, when BIND was
	  built with LMDB, zones that were deleted via
	  <command>rndc delzone</command> were removed from the
	  running server but were not removed from the new zone
	  database, so that deletion did not persist after a
	  server restart. This has been corrected. [RT #45185]
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Semicolons are no longer escaped when printing CAA and
	  URI records.  This may break applications that depend on the
	  presence of the backslash before the semicolon. [RT #45216]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      The end of life for BIND 9.12 is yet to be determined but
      will not be before BIND 9.14.0 has been released for 6 months.
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>

    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
