<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xml:id="relnotes-9.17.0"><info><title>Notes for BIND 9.17.0</title></info>
  <para>
    System-provided pthread rwlocks implementation is used by default instead of
    built-in ISC implementation of rwlocks. Please be aware that unpatched glibc
    version from 2.26 had a <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xlink:href="https://sourceware.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=23844">bug</link>
    that could cause BIND 9 to deadlock.  The fix has been released as part of
    glibc release 2.30, and various Linux distributions have patched their glibc
    version with a notable exception of Ubuntu 18.04 (Bionic) which is work in
    progress. If you are running on affected system (e.g. Ubuntu 18.04) you need
    to compile BIND 9 with --disable-pthread-rwlock until Canonical releases
    <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/glibc/+bug/1864864">fixed
    version</link>.
  </para>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.17.0-changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The <command>rndc nta -dump</command> and
	  <command>rndc secroots</command> commands now both include
	  <command>validate-except</command> entries when listing negative
	  trust anchors. These are indicated by the keyword
	  <literal>permanent</literal> in place of the expiry
	  date. [GL #1532]
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.17.0-bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Fixed re-signing issues with inline zones which resulted in
	  records being re-signed late or not at all.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.17.0-new"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When a secondary server receives a large incremental zone
	  transfer (IXFR), it can have a negative impact on query
	  performance while the incremental changes are applied to
	  the zone. To address this, <command>named</command> can now
	  limit the size of IXFR responses it sends in response to zone
	  transfer requests. If an IXFR response would be larger than an
	  AXFR of the entire zone, it will send an AXFR resonse instead.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This behavior is controlled by the <command>max-ixfr-ratio</command>
	  option - a percentage value representing the ratio of IXFR size
	  to the size of a full zone transfer. This value cannot exceed
	  100%, which is also the default. [GL #1515]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</section>
