<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, you can obtain one at https://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xml:id="relnotes-9.11.1"><info><title>Notes for BIND 9.11.1</title></info>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.11.1-security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>rndc ""</command> could trigger an assertion failure
          in <command>named</command>. This flaw is disclosed in
          (CVE-2017-3138). [RT #44924]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Some chaining (i.e., type CNAME or DNAME) responses to upstream
          queries could trigger assertion failures. This flaw is disclosed
          in CVE-2017-3137. [RT #44734]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>dns64</command> with <command>break-dnssec yes;</command>
          can result in an assertion failure. This flaw is disclosed in
          CVE-2017-3136. [RT #44653]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a server is configured with a response policy zone (RPZ)
          that rewrites an answer with local data, and is also configured
          for DNS64 address mapping, a NULL pointer can be read
          triggering a server crash.  This flaw is disclosed in
          CVE-2017-3135. [RT #44434]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A coding error in the <option>nxdomain-redirect</option>
          feature could lead to an assertion failure if the redirection
          namespace was served from a local authoritative data source
          such as a local zone or a DLZ instead of via recursive
          lookup. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2016-9778. [RT #43837]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> could mishandle authority sections
          with missing RRSIGs, triggering an assertion failure. This
          flaw is disclosed in CVE-2016-9444. [RT #43632]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> mishandled some responses where
          covering RRSIG records were returned without the requested
          data, resulting in an assertion failure. This flaw is
          disclosed in CVE-2016-9147. [RT #43548]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> incorrectly tried to cache TKEY
          records which could trigger an assertion failure when there was
          a class mismatch. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2016-9131.
          [RT #43522]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It was possible to trigger assertions when processing
          responses containing answers of type DNAME. This flaw is
          disclosed in CVE-2016-8864. [RT #43465]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Added the ability to specify the maximum number of records
          permitted in a zone (<option>max-records #;</option>).
          This provides a mechanism to block overly large zone
          transfers, which is a potential risk with slave zones from
          other parties, as described in CVE-2016-6170.
          [RT #42143]
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.11.1-changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>dnstap</command> now stores both the local and remote
          addresses for all messages, instead of only the remote address.
          The default output format for <command>dnstap-read</command> has
          been updated to include these addresses, with the initiating
          address first and the responding address second, separated by
          "-%gt;" or "%lt;-" to indicate in which direction the message
          was sent. [RT #43595]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Expanded and improved the YAML output from
          <command>dnstap-read -y</command>: it now includes packet
          size and a detailed breakdown of message contents.
          [RT #43622] [RT #43642]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If an ACL is specified with an address prefix in which the
          prefix length is longer than the address portion (for example,
          192.0.2.1/8), <command>named</command> will now log a warning.
          In future releases this will be a fatal configuration error.
          [RT #43367]
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.11.1-bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A synthesized CNAME record appearing in a response before the
          associated DNAME could be cached, when it should not have been.
          This was a regression introduced while addressing CVE-2016-8864.
          [RT #44318]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> could deadlock if multiple changes
          to NSEC/NSEC3 parameters for the same zone were being processed
          at the same time. [RT #42770]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> could trigger an assertion when
          sending NOTIFY messages. [RT #44019]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Referencing a nonexistent zone in a <command>response-policy</command>
          statement could cause an assertion failure during configuration.
          [RT #43787]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>rndc addzone</command> could cause a crash
          when attempting to add a zone with a type other than
          <command>master</command> or <command>slave</command>.
          Such zones are now rejected. [RT #43665]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>named</command> could hang when encountering log
          file names with large apparent gaps in version number (for
          example, when files exist called "logfile.0", "logfile.1",
          and "logfile.1482954169").  This is now handled correctly.
          [RT #38688]
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a zone was updated while <command>named</command> was
          processing a query for nonexistent data, it could return
          out-of-sync NSEC3 records causing potential DNSSEC validation
          failure. [RT #43247]
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.11.1-maint"><info><title>Maintenance</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The built-in root hints have been updated to include an
          IPv6 address (2001:500:12::d0d) for G.ROOT-SERVERS.NET.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes-9.11.1-misc"><info><title>Miscellaneous Notes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Authoritative server support for the EDNS Client Subnet option
          (ECS), introduced in BIND 9.11.0, was based on an early version
          of the specification, and is now known to have incompatibilities
          with other ECS implementations. It is also inefficient, requiring
          a separate view for each answer, and is unable to correct for
          overlapping subnets in the configuration.  It is intended for
          testing purposes but is not recommended for for production use.
          This was not made sufficiently clear in the documentation at
          the time of release.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</section>
