<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY Scaron "&#x160;">
<!ENTITY scaron "&#x161;">
<!ENTITY ccaron "&#x10D;">
<!ENTITY aacute "&#x0E1;">
<!ENTITY iacute "&#x0ED;">
<!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY ouml "&#xf6;">]>
<!--
 - Copyright (C) Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - See the COPYRIGHT file distributed with this work for additional
 - information regarding copyright ownership.
-->

<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"><info/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="noteversion.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="relnotes_intro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.15 is an unstable development release of BIND.
      This document summarizes new features and functional changes that
      have been introduced on this branch.  With each development release
      leading up to the stable BIND 9.16 release, this document will be
      updated with additional features added and bugs fixed.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_versions"><info><title>Note on Version Numbering</title></info>
    <para>
      Until BIND 9.12, new feature development releases were tagged
      as "alpha" and "beta", leading up to the first stable release
      for a given development branch, which always ended in ".0".
      More recently, BIND adopted the "odd-unstable/even-stable"
      release numbering convention. There will be no "alpha" or "beta"
      releases in the 9.15 branch, only increasing version numbers.
      So, for example, what would previously have been called 9.15.0a1,
      9.15.0a2, 9.15.0b1, and so on, will instead be called 9.15.0,
      9.15.1, 9.15.2, etc.
    </para>
    <para>
      The first stable release from this development branch will be
      renamed as 9.16.0. Thereafter, maintenance releases will continue
      on the 9.16 branch, while unstable feature development proceeds in
      9.17.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_platforms"><info><title>Supported Platforms</title></info>
    <para>
      To build on UNIX-like systems, BIND requires support for POSIX.1c
      threads (IEEE Std 1003.1c-1995), the Advanced Sockets API for
      IPv6 (RFC 3542), and standard atomic operations provided by the
      C compiler.
    </para>
    <para>
      The OpenSSL cryptography library must be available for the target
      platform.  A PKCS#11 provider can be used instead for Public Key
      cryptography (i.e., DNSSEC signing and validation), but OpenSSL is
      still required for general cryptography operations such as hashing
      and random number generation.
    </para>
    <para>
      More information can be found in the <filename>PLATFORMS.md</filename>
      file that is included in the source distribution of BIND 9.  If your
      compiler and system libraries provide the above features, BIND 9
      should compile and run. If that isn't the case, the BIND
      development team will generally accept patches that add support
      for systems that are still supported by their respective vendors.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_download"><info><title>Download</title></info>
    <para>
      The latest versions of BIND 9 software can always be found at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/downloads/">http://www.isc.org/downloads/</link>.
      There you will find additional information about each release,
      source code, and pre-compiled versions for Microsoft Windows
      operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_security"><info><title>Security Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  In certain configurations, <command>named</command> could crash
	  with an assertion failure if <command>nxdomain-redirect</command>
	  was in use and a redirected query resulted in an NXDOMAIN from the
	  cache. This flaw is disclosed in CVE-2019-6467. [GL #880]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The TCP client quota set using the <command>tcp-clients</command>
	  option could be exceeded in some cases. This could lead to
	  exhaustion of file descriptors. (CVE-2018-5743) [GL #615]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_features"><info><title>New Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new <command>add-soa</command> option specifies whether
	  or not the <command>response-policy</command> zone's SOA record
	  should be included in the additional section of RPZ responses.
	  [GL #865]
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_removed"><info><title>Removed Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>dnssec-enable</command> option has been deprecated and
	  no longer has any effect. DNSSEC responses are always enabled
	  if signatures and other DNSSEC data are present. [GL #866]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <command>cleaning-interval</command> option has been
	  removed.  [GL !1731]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_changes"><info><title>Feature Changes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The new <command>dnssec-keys</command> statement can now be
	  used to configure all DNSSEC trust anchors.  The older
	  <command>managed-keys</command> statement is a synonym for
	  <command>dnssec-keys</command>, retained for backward
	  compatibility. Both statements can now use the
	  keyword <command>static-key</command> in place of
	  <command>initial-key</command> if it is necessary to
	  configure trusted keys for which RFC 5011 trust anchor
	  maintenance is not to be used. [GL #6]
 	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
 	<para>
 	  <command>named</command> will now log a warning if
	  a static key is configured for the root zone, or if
	  any key is configured for "dlv.isc.org", which has been shut
	  down. [GL #6]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When static and managed DNSSEC keys were both configured for the
	  same name, or when a static key was used to
	  configure a trust anchor for the root zone and
	  <command>dnssec-validation</command> was set to the default
	  value of <literal>auto</literal>, automatic RFC 5011 key
	  rollovers would be disabled. This combination of settings was
	  never intended to work, but there was no check for it in the
	  parser. This has been corrected, and it is now a fatal
	  configuration error. [GL #868]
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  DS and CDS records are now generated with SHA-256 digests
	  only, instead of both SHA-1 and SHA-256. This affects the
	  default output of <command>dnssec-dsfromkey</command>, the
	  <filename>dsset</filename> files generated by
	  <command>dnssec-signzone</command>, the DS records added to
	  a zone by <command>dnssec-signzone</command> based on
	  <filename>keyset</filename> files, the CDS records added to
	  a zone by <command>named</command> and
	  <command>dnssec-signzone</command> based on "sync" timing
	  parameters in key files, and the checks performed by
	  <command>dnssec-checkds</command>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  JSON-C is now the only supported library for enabling JSON
	  support for BIND statistics. The <command>configure</command>
	  option has been renamed from <command>--with-libjson</command>
	  to <command>--with-json-c</command>.  Use
	  <command>PKG_CONFIG_PATH</command> to specify a custom path to
	  the <command>json-c</command> library as the new
	  <command>configure</command> option does not take the library
	  installation path as an optional argument.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_removed"><info><title>Removed Features</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  In order to clarify the configuration of DNSSEC keys,
	  the <command>trusted-keys</command> and
	  <command>managed-keys</command> statement has been
	  deprecated.  The new <command>dnssec-keys</command> should
	  be used for both types of keys.
	</para>
	<para>
	  When used with the keyword <command>initial-key</command>,
	  <command>dnssec-keys</command> has the same behavior as
	  <command>managed-keys</command>, i.e., it configures
	  a trust anchor that is to be maintained via RFC 5011.
	</para>
	<para>
	  When used with the new keyword <command>static-key</command>, it
	  has the same behavior as <command>trusted-keys</command>,
	  configuring a permanent trust anchor that will not automatically
	  be updated.  This usage is not recommended for the root key.
	  [GL #6]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_bugs"><info><title>Bug Fixes</title></info>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The <command>allow-update</command> and
	  <command>allow-update-forwarding</command> options were
	  inadvertently treated as configuration errors when used at the
	  <command>options</command> or <command>view</command> level.
	  This has now been corrected.
	  [GL #913]
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_license"><info><title>License</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND is open source software licensed under the terms of the Mozilla
      Public License, version 2.0 (see the <filename>LICENSE</filename>
      file for the full text).
    </para>
    <para>
      The license requires that if you make changes to BIND and distribute
      them outside your organization, those changes must be published under
      the same license. It does not require that you publish or disclose
      anything other than the changes you have made to our software.  This
      requirement does not affect anyone who is using BIND, with or without
      modifications, without redistributing it, nor anyone redistributing
      BIND without changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those wishing to discuss license compliance may contact ISC at
      <link
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/">
	https://www.isc.org/mission/contact/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="end_of_life"><info><title>End of Life</title></info>
    <para>
      BIND 9.15 is an unstable development branch. When its development
      is complete, it will be renamed to BIND 9.16, which will be a
      stable branch.
    </para>
    <para>
      The end of life date for BIND 9.16 has not yet been determined.
      For those needing long term support, the current Extended Support
      Version (ESV) is BIND 9.11, which will be supported until at
      least December 2021. See
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/">https://www.isc.org/downloads/software-support-policy/</link>
      for details of ISC's software support policy.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="relnotes_thanks"><info><title>Thank You</title></info>
    <para>
      Thank you to everyone who assisted us in making this release possible.
      If you would like to contribute to ISC to assist us in continuing to
      make quality open source software, please visit our donations page at
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/donate/">http://www.isc.org/donate/</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
